Welcome, thanks so much for joining us, whether you're here in person or watching online.
If you don't know me, my name is Ryan.
I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here at Canvas.
Super excited to continue our series through the book of James.
You might have noticed on your way in that the communion cups are not out like normal.
We regularly try and take communion every single week.
And this week, our plan is at the end of service just to spend some time intentionally and on purpose praying for the nation of Ukraine in light of that.
You know, part of communion is about remembering Jesus, but it's also about bringing us around the table that we've all been invited to as a family of God.
And there are believers all over the nation of Ukraine that probably would love to be able to take communion this morning and aren't going to be able to.
And so we just want to take some time to just honor them.
And, you know, Scripture says to rejoice with those who rejoice and to weep with those who weep.
And, you know, we just live in a culture where it's really easy to get focused on just our circles of influence and the things around us.
And so, you know, we're part not only of a big C church in our city, big C church in our country, but big C church around the world.
And so we definitely want to take some time to do that.
And also excited about that service in a couple of weeks just to come together with other churches and to practically say, like, it's not about turf wars.
It's not about what brand we have in our city, what our website is, what our logo is.
But it's about Jesus Christ and building his church and building his kingdom.
We say this all the time.
One of my favorite things about Canvas is we say that we want to see the kingdom of God built in the city of Winchester as it is in heaven.
And that's really one of our core values here at Canvas is to be a kingdom-focused church.
And that's not just something that we say.
It's something that we want to see manifested in our city.
So I'd also, again, just to kind of rehash some of the announcements, I'd love to invite you to be a part of that group just to pray for what might be next for our church and to kind of contribute to that.
I get questions all the time about what I think, what people think.
People want to know what I think the next chapter of our church is going to look like.
And what I've been saying is I have no clue.
But what I do know is that I'm convinced beyond a shadow of a doubt that there is a community of people here that I want to build the kingdom of God with.
Whatever that looks like, whatever kind of forms that might take over the next couple of months or even years, I know that there are people here that are real people with real lives who want to see the kingdom of God built in our city.
And as long as we have that, we've got a church.
That's all I know.
So we're going to continue our series through the book of James.
I made a joke a couple of weeks ago that I didn't want to be the guy that was going to preach through a book of the Bible for like a year.
Not that there's anything wrong with those guys.
I listen to those guys.
I find value from those guys.
It's just not me.
I didn't want to be that guy.
And then God just keeps making me do things I don't want to do.
I'm going to go backwards in the book of James this week.
We're going to spend some time in a text that we already went through.
We're going to go forward too, but we're going to go backwards so that we can go forward.
So if you have your Bibles, I'd love to have you open up to the book of James.
And the reason that I'm going to go backwards in order to go forwards is because the passage that we're going to get to this morning really is a hinge passage for the rest of the book of James.
So it's really important that we understand this passage because it's going to set us up for the rest of James' teachings.
Because James has, like I said at the beginning of this series, James has some really practical teachings.
And if we're not careful, if we don't understand how he's setting those practical teachings up, if we don't understand the foundation that he's laying for those practical teachings, it would be really easy for us to get kind of trapped in this moral concept where we just think he's addressing moral behaviors rather than heart conditions.
Which what he's going to do this morning is he's going to set us up that behavior, what we think about when we think about moral behavior and whether we're being obedient to God's word or not.
What matters is our heart condition, not the external behaviors.
And so if we don't understand that, we can get trapped in this, like, moral, religious behavior modification.
And that's not what the book of James is about.
The book of James is expounding on the teachings of Jesus and what it looks like to follow Jesus first from our hearts and then externally it produces fruit.
So hopefully that makes sense.
It might seem like I'm beating a dead horse today.
As I was kind of thinking through my notes, I'm like, man, I'm really hammering home on this one point.
But I think it's going to set us up for the rest of the book of James.
Does that make sense?
Thanks, Corey.
Let me pray and then we'll hop in.
Father, we thank you so much for this opportunity that we have to gather together with other believers,
the freedom that we have to do so and the location that we have to do so and just the resources that you provide for us.
Yeah, we're still us and we don't realize it.
We look over it all the time.
I look over it all the time.
And so, Holy Spirit, I just pray that you'd be present in this room.
As you are present in rooms all across the city of Winchester, all across our country, and all across the world this morning,
as you are sharing with each individual believer what they need to hear to better follow Jesus, to better apprentice with Jesus.
So, God, I just pray for whatever happens in this room.
I pray that it would be of you.
God, that you would get me out of the way, that you would get our worship team out of the way,
that you would increase and we would decrease for your glory, for our good.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
I'm going to be in the ESV this morning.
I normally am in the NLC, so if you've got a Bible app and you want to follow Word for Word, it should be in the ESV or it should be on the screen behind us.
As we get ready to hop into James chapter 1, I'd love to get some participation like normal.
How many of you in this room would consider yourself a bargain shopper?
We've got bargain shoppers and we've got generic people in the room.
We've got any Kirkland Signature Warriors in here.
No judgment to our fancy people.
We have, for those of you online, you know, 80% of our people are bargain shoppers, but no judgment to the rest of you.
I tend to prefer generic things except for when it comes to clothing.
And not because I'm a fashionista or because I'm good at style, but for whatever reason, clothes are the one thing that I tend to be able to notice quality differences when it comes to generic versus not generic.
And the best illustration that I have for this is, like, I'm a classic middle-aged white man, and so when fall comes around, I put on flannels.
You know, I have flannels, I put them on.
And I've got some flannels from Old Navy, and I've got a couple of L.L. Bean flannels.
And they look very similar on the outside.
Like, if you just saw me walk into the room, you'd be like, eh, like, you probably wouldn't be able to tell from 20 or 30 feet which are the Old Navy flannels or which are the L.L. Bean flannels.
But if you wash the Old Navy flannels, like, five times, that's it.
You're done.
They're gone.
Like, they are, they're no longer.
But I've got, I've got L.L. Bean flannels that are probably going to be around when I'm no longer around because those things are just different, right?
Like, they look similar on the outside, but when it comes to quality, when it comes to substance, like, they're totally different.
And if you're not tracking with the fashionista illustration, if you're like, what are we doing here, I'll transition to a different illustration.
So let's think about houses.
I've owned three houses at this point, which is way too many for a 30-year-old person to have owned.
I, you know, ministry sometimes makes you play ping-pong geographically.
But the first house that I owned was in Inwood, and it was one of those, like, new-built, Dan Ryan fast houses, right?
The second house I owned was in Wilkes-Barre, a coal mining town.
And so that house was built in, like, the 20s.
And from the outside, looking at it from the outside, the houses look pretty similar.
You wouldn't really have a whole lot of difference.
But when you go into the attic, the attic of my Inwood house looked like it was built with toothpicks and, like, glue, right?
And I'm just, like, I'm, like, looking at this thing, and I'm like, huh.
Did I make a good purchase?
Luckily, the market was hot, so I resold it.
We're good.
But you walk into that attic in Wilkes-Barre in, like, timbers, like beams, right?
Like, real, solid wood.
That house was built right.
And on the outside, they looked very similar.
But the quality is so much different.
And the reason I open up with this illustration is because I believe James is really trying to get us to understand
that there's really two versions of following Jesus.
There's two versions of Christianity that, from the outside, look very similar.
But when, upon further inspection, upon trials and temptations, as he talked about previously, upon difficulty arising, the quality is much different.
So I think what James is going to say here this morning is he's going to say, don't be deceived into moral living when you've been invited into spiritual flourishing.
Like, these are these two versions of Christianity that, on the outside, look very similar, but upon further inspection, they're totally different.
Moral living, like, behavior modification, like, just checking a few boxes, doing a few of the right things, just becoming a little bit better of a person, it looks really similar to spiritual flourishing.
It looks really similar to transformation from the inside out on the outside, like, if you just interact with people who are religious versus people who are literally being transformed from the inside out,
you're not going to see a whole lot of difference on the surface.
But when trials and temptations come, when difficulty comes, like, when real life happens, you want to be the person that's building your life from the inside out, not from the outside in.
But if we're not careful, if we don't get what James is saying here, it can be really easy for us to be tempted to just focus on the outside in rather than inside out.
So James is going to say, as we continue through this book, as we talk about external behaviors, I want you to focus on those behaviors coming from the inside out and not from the outside.
And I think, if we're being honest, many of us that have grown up in the church that might have religious backgrounds, we're not careful.
It could be really easy for us to slide into focusing on external things rather than internal things.
It could be really easy for us to focus on behavior modification rather than spiritual transformation.
And honestly, there might be some of you in this room that would say, I've never even really given Christianity a fair shot because I don't really care about the moral behavior modification.
Like, you've been taught that that's the message of Jesus, that the message of Jesus is just come and be obedient.
When in reality, the message of Jesus is come, follow me, I will give you abundant life, spiritual flourishing.
And so James is going to say, look, there's two types of, and he's talking to religious people, right?
He's talking to Jewish believers, and it would be really easy for them to slide back away from the word of truth, the message of the gospel, back into do this, don't do this.
Just do this, don't do this.
So James is going to say, hey, don't be deceived into moral living when you've been invited to spiritual flourishing.
Morality leads to hypocrisy.
It leads to anger.
It leads to bitterness.
It leads to a hard heart.
Spiritual flourishing leads to abundant life.
And then at the end, he's going to give us this illustration that's going to help us decipher whether or not we're focusing on morality or spiritual flourishing.
Does that make sense?
It's kind of the trajectory that we're going the rest of our time here in James.
So James 1, starting in verse 16, I told you we were going backwards, but we will go forward.
It says, don't be deceived, my beloved brothers.
Brothers, every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights, with whom there is no variation or shadow due to change.
Of God's own will, he brought us forth by the word of truth that we should have a kind of firstfruits of his creation.
Verse 21, he goes on and he says, therefore.
So that therefore is kind of a hinged passage connecting us to that word of truth that we should be, that human beings should be a firstfruits of all creation.
He says, therefore, put away all filthiness and rampant wickedness and receive with meekness the implanted word, which is able to save your souls.
He says, be doers of the word and not hearers only, deceiving yourselves.
There's a theme there that you can be deceived into a version of Christianity that really isn't the real thing.
He says, for if anyone is a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like a man who looks intently at his natural face in the mirror.
For he looks at himself and then goes away and at once forgets what he looked like.
But the one who looks into the perfect law, the law of liberty and perseveres, being no hearer who forgets but a doer who acts, he will be blessed in his doing.
So James says, don't be deceived into moral living when you've been invited into spiritual flourishing.
In verse 18, he says that there's this process of restoration, this process of reconciliation that God has begun in Jesus.
And he says that we are the firstfruits of that process of restoration.
Romans says that all of creation is eagerly anticipating God's reconciliation, God's restoration of all things.
And so literally, like, the trees and the waters and the animals know that, like, earth is not as it should be.
Like, they know that God has a plan to make all things right again, to restore everything back to his original creation.
But it says that we are the firstfruits of that process.
So God is in the process of making all things new again.
And that process, crazily enough, starts with us.
And how does it start with us?
Does it start with us being moral people?
Does it start with us obeying a law?
No, it starts by the word of truth, by the proclamation of the message of the gospel.
Jesus started this process of reconciliation.
He has given the invitation to all of creation to submit under his lordship,
to believe that he has done everything that was required by the law perfectly,
that we might come under that, that we might receive that word of truth,
that we might begin to be conformed back into the image of Jesus,
which was what we were created for from the very beginning.
This is spiritual flourishing.
This is what we've been invited to.
Not behavior modification, not just changing a few of our behaviors,
but literally receiving the word of truth and becoming more like Jesus for the rest of our lives.
Sin has broken God's design, and he has an eternal plan to restore all things to himself.
And that plan starts with us.
It doesn't start with us following a long list of rules.
It starts with us receiving the word of truth.
And this is a pattern that we're going to see throughout this passage.
Three times he's going to use a phrase that's very similar.
He's going to start with receive the word of truth,
and then he's going to call it the implanted word,
and later he's going to call it the perfect law of liberty.
And I think what he's doing there is he's drawing out this pattern of salvation,
this pattern of following Jesus that really resembles the story that Jesus teaches,
like about the parable of the sower.
Like he's saying, the word of truth has been passed out to all of creation.
God's word, the message of hope, the message of restoration has been given to all of creation.
And for those of us who will receive it, it becomes an implanted word.
Like we receive it, and it's like a seed that goes into good soil.
And as that good soil is watered, it leads to liberty, it leads to freedom, it leads to life.
James is saying here there's a type of following Jesus.
There's a way to follow Jesus that starts with the inside, starts with receiving the word of truth,
believing the word of truth, and then watering that word of truth in our lives until it produces fruit,
until we see that change in our behavior.
Now far too often, rather than receiving the seed of the message of Jesus,
and watering that seed, and receiving the spiritual transformation that happens from the inside out,
what's much easier on the surface is to take a couple apples, staple them to a tree.
That happens immediately, right?
Like not a problem.
But like I know because Marissa and I, we have this adventure date book.
I don't know if you guys have ever seen that.
It makes you do weird things together as a couple.
It's fun but also crazy.
And one of the things, we had to plant an herb garden.
We did like basil and sage and thyme.
Thyme, we never even got anything from the thyme thing.
But some basil and some sage started coming up, and it's dead.
Because we went away for like a weekend and forgot the water, and it's gone.
Like spiritual flourishing, like from a seed to produce fruit, like that's a process.
That takes time.
That takes investment.
That takes time, but it's so much more life-giving than just taping apples to a tree,
staking apples to a tree.
You might be able to appear like an apple tree from a distance.
But it's only going to take a day or two before the apples start dying and they start falling off the tree.
James is saying don't settle for moral behavior.
Don't settle for just changing a few things about yourself when you've been invited to spiritual flourishing.
Moral living starts from the outside and spiritual flourishing starts from the inside out.
Again, they look very similar.
But upon further inspection, it's easy for people with religious backgrounds to quickly move from inside out to outside in.
You've got to be careful.
Jeremiah 31, 33 says this, that I will put my law within them.
I will write it on their hearts, and I will be their God, and they will be my people.
This message, this word of truth that comes implanted in our hearts, the whole thing is summarized by Jesus' teaching
that we are to love the Lord our God with all of our heart, soul, mind, and strength, and to love our neighbor as ourself.
Like that is the word that's been implanted to us that grows out of us.
And James is expounding here on his brother's Sermon on the Mount.
When Jesus says, you have heard it said, and he lists a bunch of behaviors.
You have heard it said, don't murder.
And he says, but I say to you, if you hate your brother in your heart, you've committed the same sin.
And he's saying, you've heard it said, moral behavior, but I'm saying to you, it starts inside of you.
Spiritual flourishing starts by addressing the condition of your heart, not the condition of your behavior.
You have heard it said, don't commit adultery.
But I say if you burn with lust in your heart, you've committed the same thing.
See, morality cares about external things, but spirituality cares about the inside.
James is saying, don't be deceived into a version of Christianity that looks similar on the outside, but lacks substances.
The same thing, that's why he's hammering home trials in chapter one.
He's saying trials will reveal whether or not you're building your life from the inside out or from the outside in.
Again, or maybe you're here and you've never given following Jesus a chance because you've always been taught this message that it's just about morality.
It's just about changing your behavior.
It's just about being a better person.
And you've seen other Christians live this way.
And what happens when we live this way is we're pretty nasty.
We play a comparison game because we want to be good on the outside.
And since we can't be that good on the outside, we find other people that aren't as good as us.
And then we point fingers at them so that we feel better about ourselves rather than allowing the truth that we're all sinful, fallen, broken people.
And that we can't actually be good enough.
And that the word of truth is that Jesus was good enough for us.
And that it's been implanted into our hearts and that he wants to change us from the inside out.
Like, that's the invitation that you've been given.
So if you're in here and you've never given Jesus a chance, man, I want to encourage you this morning, like, reconsider.
Reconsider the invitation that you've been given.
The invitation that you've been given is not moral behavior but spiritual transformation from the inside out.
I know, again, it might feel like I'm beating a little bit of a dead horse, but it's because this passage is going to set us up for the rest of our study in James.
This is going to talk about behaviors a lot for the rest of James, but those behaviors are meant to provide an opportunity for you to diagnose whether or not you're building your life on morality or spiritual transformation.
The rest of the rest of the rest of James, when we talk about behaviors, he's going to say, these behaviors, these behaviors, the point of these behaviors is not for you to try and do better at the behaviors.
The point of these behaviors is to reveal to you what is true about your heart so that you can tend to that.
You can tend to what's on the inside.
So for the passage that he goes on to, that's what he's going to do.
He's going to give us this tool that we can use every time we're being taught about behaviors.
Anytime we have a teaching about morality, anytime we're confronted with God's word in a way that convicts us or challenges us,
he's going to give us this resource, this tool that we can use to tell whether or not we're being deceived into moral living or whether or not we're tending to our hearts.
He says in verse 22, be doers of the word, not hearers only, deceiving yourselves.
For if anyone is a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like a man who looks intently at his natural face in a mirror.
For he looks at himself and he goes away at once and he forgets what he's like.
But the one who looks into the perfect law, the law of liberty and perseveres, being no hearer who forgets but a doer who acts,
he will be blessed in his doing.
In my opinion, this is one of the best illustrations in all of Scripture.
This mirror illustration, this illustration that James gives us, he says,
when we're confronted with the teachings of Jesus, when we're confronted with things that might seem moral on the surface,
it's like a mirror that shows us what's actually true about ourselves.
Like, we can pretend that we look good all day long, but then we stand in front of the mirror, especially in the morning.
You guys all know the first trip to the mirror in the morning.
It's like, I had a better vision of what I looked like in my mind.
But the mirror reveals what is true.
And James is saying, the law of liberty, the message of Jesus, that the perfect example of Jesus reveals to us how much we fall short
and how much we can never be good enough.
And so we shouldn't just adjust the behavior here or there or walk away and forget all about it,
but we should allow that mirror to tell us what's true about ourselves so that we can address the thing that matters most.
I've randomly been getting cowlicks.
It's not a thing that I've struggled with most of my life.
I think it's because my hair is thinning.
It's, like, pretty much gone up here.
Or I've changed the way that I sleep.
I'm not sure.
One or the other.
But a couple of times I realized that I left the house without really noticing,
and, like, I had a couple of meetings with, like, people.
And they didn't say anything, which was nice of them, I think.
But then I go to, like, the bathroom at lunch or whatever, and I'm like, oh, that's not good.
That's a problem.
So that's my mom laughing at me.
It's fine.
It's sticking up right now?
I checked the mirror this morning and washed my hair because I was afraid this was going to happen.
Well, here we go.
Here we go.
All right, so you guys are fully aware of what it looks like when it happens.
So what I've been trying to do, and I did this morning, is go to the mirror, check,
and it'd be really easy for me to just forget about it, move on.
Like, oh, it's not that bad.
Another thing that I've tried, putting a hat on it, which is probably what I should have tried this morning.
But neither of those things actually address the real root of the problem.
And what I normally do and what I did this morning but apparently didn't work so the illustration might fall apart is I have to get shampoo.
I have to get down to the roots of what's actually causing the problem.
And what we want to do in religion, what we want to do in moral behavior is we want to look at ourselves in the mirror.
And a couple of things we do.
One, we forget about it.
We're like, oh, okay, sure, whatever.
Like, God says that.
I agree with that.
That makes sense.
We walk away and we don't do anything about it.
Or we take it one step further and we just address a few minor moral behaviors and put a hat on it.
Cover it up.
Don't let anybody see what's actually true about ourselves.
And what James is saying is he's saying those things, they might look okay on the outside.
Like, putting a hat on it, people aren't going to know what's actually true about yourself underneath.
But that doesn't change anything.
And when real life happens, the hat's going to fly off.
People are going to see what's true about yourself.
And so when you're confronted with God's word, when you stand in front of the mirror, let it be true.
Let it reveal what's true about yourself.
And don't seek to cover it up or just tweak a behavior here or there.
But, like, let it actually tell you what's true about your heart.
And let it change your life from the inside out.
I had a mentor in college, and I used to give him such a hard time.
Everything was a heart issue.
Like, any time I did anything that was, like, slightly off, he would say, like, you got a heart issue, man.
Like, I wouldn't clean the bathroom, and he'd be like, that's a heart issue.
I'm like, it's not a heart issue.
I was just, like, I was busy, and I didn't get around to it.
He's like, yeah, but you got roommates.
And, like, you should, when you're busy, and you should think about how your decisions affect the people around you, you should think about, are you loving your neighbor as yourself?
Like, you not cleaning the bathroom is a heart issue.
And I'm like, man, I think you're right.
I think it is a heart issue.
Like, I think I'm selfish.
I think I'm a jerk.
But, like, I loved his influence in my life, because he was, I'm so tempted to just address behaviors.
I'm so tempted to just be like, fine, you're mad that I didn't clean the bathroom?
I'll clean the bathroom.
And he's like, no, that's not the point.
The point is that you're selfish.
Like, the point isn't that you didn't do this thing.
The point is that, like, the condition of your heart isn't leaning into God's design for your life, which is to love your neighbor as yourself,
to love God with your whole heart, mind, and strength, and to love your neighbor as yourself.
And so, so often, when we're confronted with bad behaviors, we just want to fix it.
We just want to check the box.
But James is saying, no, like, when you're confronted, like, let it tell you what's true about your heart.
So, I try and, I'm just still thinking about it.
Corey, where's your head?
He left, didn't he?
Man.
All right.
So, I try and make things as memorable as possible, so you walk away from this and you don't forget what I said.
I think what he's doing in this illustration is he's giving us his tool, and here's how I would phrase it so that it's repeatable and rememberable.
I would say, James is saying here, when we're confronted with God's word, assess, agree, apply, repeat.
This is kind of a creative way of phrasing it so we don't forget it.
Assess, agree, apply, repeat.
Say that with me one time so we all remember it.
Back to the shampoo illustration.
You guys ever actually read the bottle of shampoo?
Lather, rinse, repeat, right?
Man, this is a creative talk we're doing here.
I didn't even know that was going to happen.
All right.
So, assess, he's saying here, like when we're confronted with the word of truth, the law of God, when we hear God's word, we should listen to God's word, and we should ask ourselves, what does God's word say about behaviors?
And then what does my reaction to those behaviors say about my heart?
So, what does God say about greed?
What does God say about anger?
What does God say about lust?
What does God say about the way I use my words, my sexuality, my money, my time?
Like, what does God say about those things?
And what is my attitude towards that?
Do I agree with it?
Like, am I angry about some of the things that God's asking me to do?
Do I not want to do those things?
Like, do I brush up against those things?
Why?
What does that tell me about my heart?
What does my attitude towards and behavior around this command reveal to me about the attitude of my heart?
I'll say that again because I think that's a really important diagnostic question.
What does my attitude towards or my behavior around this command reveal to me about my heart?
He says, James says you should listen to the word of God.
You should look intently in the mirror.
You should see what is true about you, what is true about yourself, and how you're living.
He says, assess, here.
He says, agree.
This is the biblical practice of confession.
Confession means saying the same thing.
Like, we need to learn to get to a point over time in our relationship with God where we can learn to believe that God's ways are better than our ways.
Like, there is going to be times when you're going to come across a command from God, and you're going to be like, I don't want to do that.
I don't like that.
It doesn't make sense to me.
I don't understand why he would do that thing.
But over time, as you invest, as you water, as you mature in your relationship with God from the inside out, we should be growing in our understanding that God's ways are better than our ways.
Like, when we brush up against a command and say, I don't want to do that, I don't like that, we should ask ourselves, why?
Why is that?
And will applying this truth conform me into the image of Jesus?
Will it make me better at loving God and loving others?
Because that is our ultimate aim in life, to be conformed to the image of Jesus.
So, assess, listen to God's word.
Like, actually let it tell you what's true about yourself.
And this is an intentional practice.
This is a discipline.
Like, for those of us that read the word on a regular basis, it's really easy for you to just, like, scroll through a paragraph and check a box.
I do that sometimes in my Bible reading plan.
I'm just like, I just got to get through it today.
No, like, let it speak truth into your life.
Let it confront areas of your life that aren't like Jesus.
Let it tell you.
And then learn to agree with it.
Learn to believe that God's ways are better than your ways.
Assess, agree, apply.
This is the biblical practice of repentance.
So, if confession is we say the same thing that God is saying, we believe what he says, then applying or repentance is going in the same direction.
So, it's acknowledging, like, I've been going in a different direction than God has commanded.
I'm going to agree that his way is better than my way, and I'm going to take practical steps in the right direction.
And James here, in this illustration, is he's giving us the framework for how we should view God's word for the rest of our lives.
This is it.
When we're confronted with God's word, this is what we should do.
We should allow it to tell us what is true about ourselves.
We should allow it to tell us when we're not being conformed into the image of Jesus.
We should learn to agree with what God says, even when we don't always like it.
Wrestle with that.
Why is it?
Am I understanding the text rightly?
Like, do I understand what God's asking me to do and why he's asking me to do it?
And if I still don't agree with it, why is that?
And do this in community, because there's value to brothers and sisters in Christ helping you learn to agree with God's word.
And then take practical steps in the right direction.
And then I would say this.
Don't be discouraged when you take two steps forward and one step back, because we're broken.
We're sinners.
We fall short.
And that's the word of truth, that Jesus came and was perfect on our behalf.
We don't have to be perfect.
We just take steps in the right direction.
And when we fall and when we mess up, we give ourselves grace and we give others grace.
And we stand back up and we keep walking in the right direction.
Assess.
Agree.
Apply.
Repeat.
I got to witness this up close and personal a week or two ago in my microchurch.
And if you are not in a microchurch, if you don't have, like, a small group of people, it doesn't have to be sanctioned by canvas.
But if you don't have, like, a group of people that you do life with and talk about Jesus with, man, I would encourage you to find that.
And if I can help you find that, if you're like, hey, I don't have that and I want that and I can't find it on my own, please reach out to us.
We'll try and help you find it.
But it's so, so important.
And this week we started a conversation on spiritual disciplines.
And we talked, because I'm a cranky old person and I act way older than I look, I was like, let's start with Sabbath.
Let's talk about the Jewish practice of Sabbath that New Testament Christians completely ignore.
And it'll be fun.
And everybody was like, yay, Sabbath.
Anyway, I thought that joke was going to be funnier than it was.
It wasn't.
And so we studied the Sabbath together and we talked about, like, why does God command this to Jews and does he command it to New Testament Christians?
And if he does, are we living it out?
And we had this really intense discussion.
And this person, this person in my small group said, two weeks ago when you said we were going to talk about Sabbath, I thought, I don't want to do that.
This is a waste of time.
It's an Old Testament command that doesn't apply to my life.
And she said, and now I believe that it's a command that I've been disobeying.
And me and my family are like, we're going to try and take steps to start applying this command that I believe we've been disobeying in our lives.
I'm like, this, do you see this?
This is a pattern.
This is assess, agree, apply.
Like, she's like, I sat under God's word.
Like, I heard what he had to say about this thing that I've never thought about before.
And I think he says something that doesn't really line up with how I've been living my life.
And it's going to be hard.
I've got kids and a schedule and life.
But I think, I think, I think I believe that if I do what God says, it's actually going to be better for me than if I do what I want to do.
And then let's take steps of practical obedience in the right direction.
This, this is spiritual flourishing.
See, morality would say, yeah, God says rest is important.
And maybe I'll, like, maybe I'll delete my Instagram app for a couple of weeks because I spend too much time on it.
Or, yeah, rest, God says rest is important.
But I'm better at resting than that person is.
And so I'm good.
And we walk away from God's word.
And we don't let it transform us.
We don't let it tell us what's true about ourselves.
And James is saying, don't, don't be deceived.
Don't be deceived into moral living when you've been invited into spiritual flourishing.
Allow the word of God to tell you what's true about your heart.
And then tend to your heart.
Because that's what God cares about.
God cares about your heart, not your behavior.
And when you address your heart, your behavior will change.
When you allow God to begin to transform you from the inside out, that's when things get different.
And at the, at the end of James' brother's famous teaching, the Sermon on the Mount,
he gives an illustration that I think perfectly sums up everything that we've been talking about.
What better thing to end with than the end of Jesus' most famous sermon?
See, at the end of this sermon where he's hammering home the same point that James is hammering home,
where he's saying, you've heard it said, behavior, but I say to you, heart condition.
You've heard it said, behavior, but I say to you, heart condition.
You've heard it said, outside matters more than inside, but I say to you, inside matters more than outside.
Because when you address the inside, the outside will actually change, will have lasting change that matters.
You've heard it said, it's what you build.
But I say to you, it's what you build on.
Jesus, at the end of his sermon, says,
Everyone then who hears these words of mine and does them will be like a wise man who built his house on a rock.
And the rain fell, and the floods came, and the winds blew and beat on that house, but it did not fall.
Why?
Because it was founded on the rock.
It was focused on the internal rather than the external.
It was focused on heart transformation rather than behavior modification.
But everyone who hears these words of mine and does not do them will be like a foolish man who built his house on the sand.
And the rain fell, floods came, the winds blew and beat against this house, and it fell.
And great was the fall of it.
See, both those houses look pretty similar on the outside.
Probably easier to build the one on the sand.
It didn't take as long.
It went up faster.
Behavior modification is easier to do in a quicker way.
But the spiritual transformation building our lives on the foundation that is Jesus.
That's what we've been invited to.
And that is a lifelong process that's done in relationship, and it's so much more freeing and life-giving than religious behavior modification.
That's what you've been invited into.
And so maybe you're here and you've never really given Jesus a chance.
Or maybe you thought you were giving him a chance by just doing this behavior modification thing, by just trying to become a better person.
I think James is saying, like, don't be deceived.
Don't be deceived into believing that God cares about the external more than he cares about the internal.
That, like, this word of truth, he wants to preach this message of truth over you, that Jesus has accomplished everything that we couldn't accomplish.
And he wants you to receive that truth that becomes implanted into your hearts.
And when it becomes implanted into your hearts, it leads to true freedom, to true life.
That's the invitation of Jesus.
Not become a better person.
Follow the way of Jesus.
Learn to allow him to transform you from the inside out.
So if you're here and you've never considered the word of truth, the announcement of Jesus,
there's an invitation there.
And what do we do when we want to follow an invitation?
We respond.
I want to go that way.
I want to try this thing out.
I want to print this under the way of Jesus.
I just encourage you, man.
If that's you, I'd love to talk to you about that.
I'd love to help you take steps into that process.
Or maybe you're here and you've been churchgoer your whole life.
You've been a follower of Jesus your whole life.
Or for a while, at least.
You're probably like me.
It's probably really easy for you to skim through Scripture, look at yourself in the mirror real quick, and believe.
And don't be deceived into thinking that that's true spiritual flourishing.
Because that's tiring and exhausting over time when you just keep doing this thing where you try and make yourself better in this area and in this area and in this area.
When in reality, what we've been invited to is to allow the Word of God, not to make us think about how we can change our behavior, but to make us think about what it says about our hearts.
To invest in our hearts, in our relationship with God, that we might learn to love God with all of our heart, soul, mind, and strength.
And then love our neighbor as ourself.
And this is a lifelong process that's done in relationship.
And it's so much better than any moral modification that you might attempt.
So don't be deceived, brothers, sisters.
Let's receive and accept the invitation of Jesus.
Not for moral behavior modification, but for spiritual flourishing.
Let's pray.
Father, thank you for this opportunity that we have to stand in front of the mirror.
It's what we do every Sunday here.
It's what we most, many individuals in this room do on a daily basis.
When they sit in your presence in prayer and sit with the Scriptures in front of them,
we stand in front of them here and we just let you tell us what's true about ourselves.
And when you do, you don't do it in condemnation, guilt, shame.
You do it to invite us into true freedom, into true spiritual flourishing.
So, God, let us sit in front of the mirror, understand what's true about ourselves in light of you.
Agree with what you say, like, agree that what you say is better.
Then apply it, take steps in the right direction.
Say the same things that you say and go in the same direction that you go in.
And, God, when we fall, we trip up.
And we have brothers and sisters around us who pick us up
and encourage us to keep moving forward for your glory.
It's our good.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Hey, guys.
Ryan stole some of my thunder that I was going to talk about
changing up communion time today a little bit.
But something I want to echo, I hope you guys, I hope I'm not solo in this,
but I was super convicted with the Holy Spirit's word today through Ryan.
Something I saw earlier in the week floating around was a quote from R.C. Sproul
that just echoes kind of the point Ryan's driving home through the book of James
is the idea of it's one thing to believe in God.
It's another thing entirely to believe God.
Think about that.
It's one thing to believe in God.
It's another thing altogether to believe God.
So as we kind of take that idea with us today, we're going to spend some time.
Ryan left me 30 seconds.
So we're going to spend some time today.
I was thinking, I'm going to read a quick verse.
Romans 8 came to mind today when thinking about the church in Ukraine,
believers in Ukraine.
But not only the believers in Ukraine, but Russia, Europe.
These people that are in the midst of calamity, whether right, wrong, what have you,
are in the midst of this.
And we need to remember the church as a whole, the global church, as we pray today.
Romans 8.35, can anything ever separate us from Christ's love?
Does it mean he no longer loves us if we have trouble or calamity?
Or are persecuted, or hungry, or destitute, or in danger, or threatened with death?
As the Scriptures say, for your sake, we are killed every day.
We are being slaughtered like sheep.
No, despite all these things, the overwhelming victory is ours through Christ who loved us.
So I encourage you today, I'll close in prayer, but I encourage you to take 10 seconds.
We'll run over 30 seconds to just bow your head, close your eyes,
and spend some time with the Father just remembering the global church,
remembering the suffering of our brothers and sisters.
That one day, I don't mean, I always get on this kick, but that one day could be us.
I mean, we do, we live in a place of privilege.
We live in the United States.
We've never really suffered like the global church has.
That's not to say one day that suffering won't be ours.
So spend time in prayer with the Father.
I'll pick it up.
We'll close in prayer, and I'll spend some more time with you guys real quick.
We'll close in prayer, and I'll see you guys real quick.
Dear Heavenly Father, as people are continuing to send prayers up, Lord,
we pray for our brothers and sisters around the world, especially in Ukraine.
Lord, give us eyes that you have, the love that you have for people,
no matter if we see eye to eye with them or if we have our differences, Lord,
that we have the love, grace, and mercy that you first taught us.
Thank for these people.
Give them mercy and grace as we travel forward into the weak,
maybe a light to a dark world.